<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Salsa Handbook - blog</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/</id><updated>2021-09-06T13:57:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Announcing new videobooks</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/videobooks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-06T12:34:56-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T12:48:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Marisol Enchufa</name></author><id>tag:salsahandbook.github.io,2021-09-06:/output/videobooks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Announcing the new video book format and the first three editions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;INTRODUCING THE VIDEOBOOK FORMAT&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p float="left"&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;
  &lt;img src="images/book_covers/vbook1_cover_1400x2240.jpeg" width="250" /&gt;
  &lt;img src="images/book_covers/vbook2_cover_1400x2243.jpeg" width="250" /&gt;
  &lt;img src="images/book_covers/vbook3.cover_1400x2243.jpeg" width="250" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This format is an ebook that contains embedded videos. Each animated video demonstrates a dance element, such as a dance pattern, step, or handhold. Most dance elements are shown from more than one camera angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why the videobook?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The videobook is ideal for visual learners. Some people learn by watching a demonstration.  Some people learn best by imitating in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scrubbable video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each animation can be "scrubbed". Moving the cursor or playhead across the video timeline manually is called video scrubbing. Scrubbing is a great way to review the video at your own pace, something that can be a challenge to do with other video content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to use video scrubbing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is super easy -- barely an inconvenience. All you need to do is move your cursor above the scrub bar and drag it in the desired direction to navigate through video clips.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Succinct text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each video is accompanied with just enough text to explain each video. Links are provided to longer form content that goes into more depth or provides additional context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Streamlined presentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having perused hundreds of instructional salsa dance videos, I can attest to how challenging it can be for a beginner to follow the movements demonstrated by even the best professional salsa dance instructors. Many dance instructors are well suited to teaching intermediate to advanced level dancers; however they often use styling that is overkill for the beginner.  Beginners can get confused by elaborate stylings or lose sight of what is essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advance Review Copy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contact me if you would like a free ARC to review or to preview for a larger purchase for your club or educational institution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Please share your feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can tell me what you think by tweet or email.  Your feedback is so appreciated!  We value your opinion!  If this format is helpful, then more content will be added. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would you like to see?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tweet your feedback to &lt;strong&gt;@salsahandbook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email your feedback to &lt;strong&gt;salsahandbook&lt;/strong&gt; (at) &lt;strong&gt;gmail&lt;/strong&gt; (dot) &lt;strong&gt;com&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THANK YOU!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where to find?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/author/marisol-enchufa/id1513830368"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/handbook-of-salsa-dance-basic-step/id1577664305"&gt;Basic Step&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/handbook-of-salsa-dance-right-turn/id1583340370"&gt;Right Turn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/handbook-of-salsa-dance-crossbody-patterns/id1583344155"&gt;Crossbody Patterns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/s?i=digital-text&amp;amp;rh=p_27%3AMarisol+Enchufa&amp;amp;s=relevancerank&amp;amp;text=Marisol+Enchufa"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B095SWSZN6"&gt;Basic Step&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B097Q525CB"&gt;Right Turn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B09FH1Y5DQ"&gt;Crossbody Patterns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Help me choose my illustration models</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/partner-pairings.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-20T12:34:56-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T13:57:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Marisol Enchufa</name></author><id>tag:salsahandbook.github.io,2021-03-20:/output/partner-pairings.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article asks the reader to vote on their favorite dance couple from a list of digital models.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;PICK YOUR FAVORITE ILLUSTRATION MODEL&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear reader. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a favor to ask of you. I am redoing all of the illustrations in my books. I am about to re-render all of the illustrations with new models.  Could you kindly take a moment and tell me your favorite models by tweeting me at &lt;strong&gt;@salsahandbook&lt;/strong&gt;?  Your feedback would be appreciated very much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the new illustrations I am using stylized characters to model the dance poses.  I have narrowed it down to four &lt;code&gt;Leader&lt;/code&gt; models and three &lt;code&gt;Follower&lt;/code&gt; models, along with eight different &lt;code&gt;Follower&lt;/code&gt; wardrobes and five different &lt;code&gt;Leader&lt;/code&gt; wardrobes. Nine pairings of these model and wardrobe combinations are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please express your preference!&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just scroll down to see the choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We value your opinion!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THANK YOU!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PICK YOUR FAVORITE!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please pick your favorite pairing from the following list!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tweet your selection to &lt;strong&gt;@salsahandbook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email your feedback to &lt;strong&gt;salsahandbook&lt;/strong&gt; (at) &lt;strong&gt;gmail&lt;/strong&gt; (dot) &lt;strong&gt;com&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 1:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/1_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 2:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/2_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 3:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/3_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 4:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/4_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 5:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/5_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 6:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/6_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 7:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/7_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 8:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/8_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Pairing 9:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:left"&gt;&lt;img src="images/pairings/8a_front_left.png" width="375" height="655" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;WHY&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've published several reference books about salsa dance. Links are provided below in the More Reading section. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I illustrated those books using a quick and easy posing tool called Magic Poser. This was the best posing tool for what I needed at the time. However the salsa handbooks have now outgrown that tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I very highly recommend Magic Poser. It provided pluggable body, hair, and wardrobe combinations, allowed posing two models simultaneously, and was very easy to use. The inverse kinematics of their rigged characters is excellent. I was able to create all of those poses using touch gestures on an iPhone 5s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was time to bite the bullet and learn a software that could provide flexibility I wanted to have to improve these illustrations. I have finally ramped up the rather steep learning curve on that software.  I am now in the final stage. The next step is to choose from among several candidate models to pick the ones to use for re-rendering the illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about salsa dance check out these books (now using the new models in illustrations):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-positions/id1513830159"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Dance-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B084FBB468"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=yBXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-patterns/id1513834201"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-1"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Patterns-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B093P9WS9H"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=1BXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Butterfly Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B094311BLN"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Salsa Dance Positions</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-positions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-01T12:34:56-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T13:57:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Marisol Enchufa</name></author><id>tag:salsahandbook.github.io,2020-08-01:/output/salsa-positions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article explains the salsa dance position.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;What is a salsa dance position&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The salsa dance position is a fundamental element of partner dance. Salsa dance elements include the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handholds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stylings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combinations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A salsa dance position comprises the orientation of the dancers with respect to each other and the handhold. For more about handholds, see &lt;a href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-handholds.html"&gt;this article, which is all about salsa dance handholds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aspects of dancer orientation include what direction each dancer is facing, whether the dancers are in a handhold, at what level are the hands held, and the direction of eye gaze. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We refer to the leader as &lt;em&gt;Leader&lt;/em&gt; and to the follower as &lt;em&gt;Follower&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Facing Each Other&lt;/em&gt; is a common orientation.  Here, the dancers are apart and facing each other. &lt;em&gt;Apart&lt;/em&gt; means that they are not touching. That also implies that they are not holding hands. That is, they are not in a &lt;a href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-handholds.html"&gt;handhold&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Apart_FEO_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a more advanced position where the dancers are &lt;em&gt;Facing Same Direction&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Side By Side&lt;/em&gt;, and with &lt;em&gt;Leader On Left&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Closed_R_to_R_Hammerlock_SBS_LOL.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Why the dance position is important&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salsa dance is a pleasing transition through a series of positions. Every salsa dance pattern begins and ends in a dance position. Expert salsa dancers know how to get into and out of myriad salsa dance positions in interesting ways. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing how to transition through positions in fun and pleasing ways can help increase your salsa dance repertoire.  This is facilitated by knowing your dance positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How the dance position fits into patterns and combinations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many salsa dance enthusiasts, salsa dance is the aesthetically pleasing progression through a series of dance combinations over the course of a song. A salsa dance combination is comprised of two or more salsa dance patterns, each pattern covering two bars of music. Every salsa dance pattern begins and ends in a dance position. Therefore, the salsa dance pattern is a pleasing transition from a start position to an end position over eight beats of music. Because salsa dance is made up of combinations, and combinations are made up of patterns, and a dance pattern begins in a position and ends in a position, one can view salsa dance positions as a fundamental building block of the salsa dance combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;More examples of basic salsa dance positions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Half Closed Position&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dancers are facing each other, with Leader's right hand on Follower's left upper back, and Follower's left hand on Leader's left shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_Closed_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Open Position&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An "open position" is a class of positions where the dancers are not in a closed position, typically in a handhold, and typically facing each other. Because this particular open position is so common it is often referred to simply as *Open Position. The dancers are holding both pairs of hands. This handhold is also referred to as a parallel handhold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Open_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Half Open Right to Left&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a variation of the Open Position where the dancers are holding only one pair of hands. Leader's right hand is holding Follower's left hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_Open_R_to_L_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Half Open Left to Right&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another variation of the Open Position where the dancers are holding only one pair of hands. Leader's left hand is holding Follower's right hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_Open_L_to_R_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Handshake&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this position the dancers are facing each other, in a right to right handhold. This is one of those positions that is named after the handhold. However, it is possible to be in an orientation other than the one shown here. See the Salsa Handbooks for examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Handshake_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Reverse Handshake&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this position the dancers are facing each other, in a left to left handhold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Handshake_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Crosshold&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another position that is named after the handhold. This is a type of open position where the dancers facing each other, holding both pairs of hands, and where the hands are crossed.  The handhold is right hand to right hand, left hand to left hand, with Leader's right hand over Leader's left hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Crosshold_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this position appears from an overhead view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Crosshold_overhead.PNG" width="300" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leader can remember this as "left to left, right to right, right over left".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reverse Crosshold&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a variation of the Crosshold, where Leader's left hand is over Leader's right hand. Leader can remember it as "left to left, right to right, left over right".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Crosshold_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this handhold appears from an overhead view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Crosshold_overhead.PNG" width="300" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many positions have inversions which mirror the original position, or where the handhold is inverted. This is why it is helpful to know how to breakdown a position into its parts, so that when introduced to a new position you can realize that it is a variation of a position that you already know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crossed Parallel Hold&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of the more unusual positions. It uses a kind of parallel hold but where the hands are crossed.  The handhold is left to right and right to left, with Leader's left hand over Leader's right hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note on naming: truthfully there doesn't seem to be a standard name for this handhold. This is one of those handholds where it can be simpler to just explicitly describe the hold, as in "right to left, left to right, left over right". Or, for its inverse variation, as "left to right, right to left, right over left". The section below on Shorthand delves more into this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Parallel_Hold_LLHS.PNG" width="300" height="471" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a closeup view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Parallel_Hold_LLHS_CLOSEUP.PNG" width="130" height="180" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this handhold appears from an overhead view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Parallel_Hold_overhead.PNG" width="350" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask, do people really get into that hold? Is it useful? The answer would be yes, and yes. This handhold can be entered when performing a double handed turn. The variation of this where the hold is inverted (Leader's right hand over Leader's left hand) is obtained when perfoming the double turn in the opposite spin direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple handhold in a facing each other orientation can transform into another interesting position just by modifying the orientation of the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a position involving a right to left, left to right hand hold at high level. This is essentially the same handhold as is used in the standard open position. Only the orientation of the dancers and the height level of the handhold has changed. If you guessed that this position can be obtained by a transition from the Open Position, you would be correct!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/fsd_lib_reverse_parallel_hold_high.png" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a position involving a left to left, right to right handhold, where the dancers are facing the same direction, with Leader in back, and Follower in front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Butterfly_FSD_LIB_High.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is another application of the left to left, right to right handhold, which we already saw previously above. In this position the dancers are facing the same direction and side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Closed_R_to_R_Hammerlock_SBS_LOL.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is yet another left to left, right to left handhold, where the dancers are facing the same direction and with Leader in front, Follower in back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_L_Butterfly__Half_R_Self_Neck_Loop_LOW.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the last three positions are using the same handhold, you might guess that there is a way to transition from each of these positions to each of the others -- and you would be right. This is one of the fun aspects of salsa dance, figuring out how to enter and exit positions in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shorthand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other positions not shown here. Many positions do not have commonly accepted names. Because there are so many possible positions it is useful to use a shorthand system for describing positions that do not have common names.  It is also useful for providing a standard terminology for introducing common positions that do have a standard name to new dancers who are still just learning the basics. The &lt;a href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-handbooks.html"&gt;Salsa Handbooks&lt;/a&gt; on which this article is based use a shorthand system for referring to the dancers and their orientation. Those books provide a comprehensive overview of that shorthand notation system. This section gives a brief introduction to a subset of that shorthand notation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facing Each Other (FEO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facing Opposite Directions (FOD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Side By Side (SBS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader In Front (LIF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader In Back (LIB)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader On Right (LOF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader On Left (LOL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader's Left Hand (LLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader's Right Hand (LLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follower's Left Hand (FLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follower's Right Hand (FLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right to Right (R to R)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left to Left (L to L)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left to Right (L to R)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right to Left (R to L)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader's right hand over Leader's left hand (LRH/LLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader's left hand over Leader's right hand (LRH/LLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine all the ways in which you can combine these orientations and handholds. That gives a hint as to the number of possible positions. It turns out that there are many many positions! For a comprehensive compendium of salsa dance positions, see the &lt;a href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-handbooks.html"&gt;Handbook of Salsa Dance: Positions&lt;/a&gt;, links to which are also given below. Although that handbook is comprehensive, it is still not exhaustive! There are other positions not included there.  That is why it is useful to have a system for breaking down a position into consitituent parts. This makes it possible to not only learn novel positions, but to invent new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a position where the dancers are in a handhold, and where the dancers are &lt;em&gt;Facing Same Direction&lt;/em&gt; (FSD), &lt;em&gt;Side By Side&lt;/em&gt; (SBS), and &lt;em&gt;Leader On Left&lt;/em&gt; (LOL). Leader's right hand is to Follower's right hand (&lt;em&gt;Right to Right&lt;/em&gt;), and Leader's left hand is to Follower's left hand (&lt;em&gt;Left to Left&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Closed_R_to_R_Hammerlock_SBS_LOL.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the shorthand we can succinctly describe this position as &lt;em&gt;FSD SBS LOL, R to R, L to L&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All salsa dance patterns begin and end in a dance position. Having this insight makes it easier to assimilate a new dance pattern. A first step in breaking down a dance pattern is to observe how it begins and ends. Understanding the start and end position of a pattern makes it easier to learn the middle part of the pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about salsa dance check out these books:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-positions/id1513830159"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Dance-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B084FBB468"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=yBXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-patterns/id1513834201"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-1"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Patterns-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B093P9WS9H"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=1BXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Butterfly Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B094311BLN"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Salsa Dance Hand Holds</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-handholds.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-11T12:34:56-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T13:57:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Marisol Enchufa</name></author><id>tag:salsahandbook.github.io,2020-07-11:/output/salsa-handholds.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article introduces basic handholds of salsa dance.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Handholds are a fundamental element of partner dance. Salsa dance elements include the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handholds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stylings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combinations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A handhold is involved anytime the dancers hold hands. This article covers the most common handholds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First some terminology.  We refer to the leader as Leader.  We refer to the follower as Follower.
We use a shorthand to specify handholds. Unless specified or apparent from context, a position or element is relative to the Leader perspective. For example, unless specified otherwise and not clear from context, right hand (RH) refers to Leader's right hand (LRH). RH/LH means Leader’s right hand over Leader’s left hand. We do sometimes make these explicit. For example, FRH refers to the Follower’s right hand, and FRH/FLH means that Follower’s right hand is over Follower’s left hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some holds don't involve a handhold. The half closed position is such a hold. In the half closed position, one of Leader's hands is on Follower's upper back, and one of Follower's hands is on Leader's shoulder. No handhold here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_Closed_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note also that a lot of interesting dance moves do not require a handhold. Suppose the dancers are facing each other. In this position, each dancer could be performing steps, turns, combs, kicks, and myriad stylings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Apart_FEO_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, this article focuses on handholds. Many salsa dance positions involve a handhold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;List of handholds we'll cover here&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the handholds we'll cover here, by their common names:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parallel Hold&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half Open, Right to Left&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half Open, Left to Right&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handshake&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reverse Handshake&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crosshold&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reverse Crosshold&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These names are intuitive but can actually be somewhat confusing if you are not well practiced with the variations.  It can be simpler when you observe that every handhold consists of either one or two pairs of hands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Left to Right" means Leader left hand (LLH) to Follower right hand (FRH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Right to Left" means Leader right (LRH) hand to Follower left hand (FLH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Right to Right" means Leader right hand to Follower right hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Left to Left" means Leader left hand to Follower left hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives the following combinations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Right, Right to Left&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right to Left&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Right&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right to Right&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Left&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Left, Right to Right. LRH/LLH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Left, Right to Right. LLH/LRH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Right, Right to Left, LLH/LRH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to Right, Right to Left, LRH/LLH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first seven correspond to the named handholds listed above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might think that there are only six combinations of ways that hands can be held; however, it turns out that there are more variations depending on whether one pair of hands is over or under the other pair of hands. The crosshold can be held in two ways. In one variation, Leader's right hand (LRH) is over Leader's left hand (LLH), which we designate as LRH/LLH.  In the other variation, LLH/LRH. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also two additional handholds that don't correspond to any of the handholds in the named list.  Handholds 8 and 9 are a variation of the parallel hold where the hands are crossed.  This can occur after a double handed full turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we'll examine each of these more closely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Left to Right, Right to Left&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This handhold is so common it is usually given a common name. It is also known as &lt;strong&gt;Parallel Hold&lt;/strong&gt;.  The most common position using this is a type of open position, shown here: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Open_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular open position is used so often it is often referred to simply as &lt;strong&gt;Open Position&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Right to Left&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common position in which this handhold is used is shown here, and is known as &lt;strong&gt;Half Open, Right to Left&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_Open_R_to_L_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Left to Right&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common position in which this handhold is used is shown here, and is known as &lt;strong&gt;Half Open, Left to Right&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_Open_L_to_R_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Right to Right&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common position in which this handhold is used is shown here, and is known as &lt;strong&gt;Handshake&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Handshake_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Left to Left&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common position in which this handhold is used is shown here, and is known as &lt;strong&gt;Reverse Handshake&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Handshake_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Left to Left, Right to Right. LRH/LLH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common position in which this handhold is used is shown here, and is known as &lt;strong&gt;Crosshold&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Crosshold_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this handhold appears from an overhead view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Crosshold_overhead.PNG" width="300" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Left to Left, Right to Right. LLH/LRH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a variation of the crosshold, where Leader's left hand is over Leader's right hand. This position is also known as &lt;strong&gt;Reverse Crosshold&lt;/strong&gt;. However, not everyone might know that term, so sometimes it is just referred to as "left to left, right to right, left over right".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Crosshold_LLHS.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this handhold appears from an overhead view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Crosshold_overhead.PNG" width="300" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Left to Right, Right to Left, LLH/LRH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of the more unusual handholds.  It is sometimes called a &lt;strong&gt;Reverse Parallel Hold&lt;/strong&gt;; however it is actually a kind of parallel hold but where the hands are crossed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note on naming: truthfully there doesn't seem to be a standard name for this handhold. This is one of those handholds where it can be simpler to just explicitly describe the hold, as in "right to left, left to right, left over right". Or, for its inverse variation, as "right to left, left to right, right over left". A better common name might be "Crossed Parallel". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Parallel_Hold_LLHS.PNG" width="300" height="471" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a closeup view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Parallel_Hold_LLHS_CLOSEUP.PNG" width="130" height="180" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this handhold appears from an overhead view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Reverse_Parallel_Hold_overhead.PNG" width="350" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask, do people really get into that hold? Is it useful? The answer would be yes, and yes. This handhold can be entered when performing a double handed turn. The other variation of this where LRH/LLH is obtained when perfoming the double turn in the opposite spin direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you adjust the orientation of the dancers, these handholds suddenly transform into interesting positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a Right to Left, Left to Right hand hold at high level. This is essentially the same handhold as is used in the standard open position. Only the orientation of the dancers and the height level of the handhold has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/fsd_lib_reverse_parallel_hold_high.png" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a Left to Left, Right to Right handhold, where the dancers are facing the same direction, with Leader in back, and Follower in front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Butterfly_FSD_LIB_High.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is another Left to Left, Right to Right handhold, where the dancers are facing the same direction and side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Closed_R_to_R_Hammerlock_SBS_LOL.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is yet another Left to Left, Right to Left handhold, where the dancers are facing the same direction and with Leader in front, Follower in back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/Half_L_Butterfly__Half_R_Self_Neck_Loop_LOW.PNG" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the last three positions are using the same handhold, you might guess that there is a way to transition from each of these positions to each of the others -- and you would be right. This is one of the fun aspects of salsa dance, figuring out how to enter and exit positions in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many salsa dance positions involve a handhold. One way to quickly breakdown a dance position is to observe whether it involves a handhold, and if so, which one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about salsa dance check out these books:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-positions/id1513830159"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Dance-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B084FBB468"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=yBXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-patterns/id1513834201"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-1"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Patterns-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B093P9WS9H"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=1BXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Butterfly Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B094311BLN"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Salsa Dance Styles</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-styles.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-13T12:34:56-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T13:57:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Marisol Enchufa</name></author><id>tag:salsahandbook.github.io,2020-06-13:/output/salsa-styles.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article introduces common styles of salsa dance.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are many styles of salsa dance. They can differ in many ways.  Some of the ways in which they may differ are very nuanced. However, there are two primary defining characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The traveling style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The timing used for the break step in the basic step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The break step determines when to change directions in the basic step. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Break Step&lt;/strong&gt;: A two step sequence in which the second step is in the opposite direction as the first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In On1 timing, Leader will break forwards on beat one, and break backwards on beat five. Follower does the opposite, breaking back on beat one and forwards on beat five. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;On1 LA Style Basic Step:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;iframe src='https://gfycat.com/ifr/HighlevelMammothIraniangroundjay' frameborder='0' scrolling='no' allowfullscreen width='640' height='412'&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href="https://gfycat.com/highlevelmammothiraniangroundjay"&gt;Dance Dojo via Gfycat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On1 basic step&lt;/strong&gt;: Uses 8 beats to complete; with the feet alternating step on beats 1,2,3; pause on beat 4; stepping on beats 5,6,7; pausing on beat 8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Los Angeles Style is often referred to as LA Style and also as West Coast Style. LA style salsa is an eight beat dance made up of six steps and two pauses. The eight beats cover two musical bars. It is an “On1” style because its break step is on the first beat of the musical bar. Steps 4 and 8 are paused. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common way of counting the steps over two musical bars is “1-2-3, 5-6-7”. Another common way of counting the steps is to recite "quick quick slow, quick quick slow", with each &lt;code&gt;quick&lt;/code&gt; taking one beat, and each &lt;code&gt;slow&lt;/code&gt; taking two beats. The following animation illustrates the On1 Basic Step for the Leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;On1 Basic Step:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/gifs/ManBasicAnimationSlowSmall.gif" alt="On1 Basic Step for Leader"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.salsa-dancing-addict.com/salsa-timing.html"&gt;credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following animation illustrates the On1 Basic Step for the Leader and Follower, from the perspective of Leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;On1 Basic Step for Leader and Follower facing each other:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/gifs/basic-step-combined-slow.gif" alt="On1 Basic Step for Leader and Follower"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.salsa-dancing-addict.com/combined-basic-salsa-step.html"&gt;credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some styles have their break step on the second beat of the musical bar. For this reason, many refer to such styles as “On2”.  In On2 timing, Leader is breaking on beats two and six.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On2 basic step&lt;/strong&gt;: Uses 8 beats to complete but breaking on beat two of the musical bar, equivalently on beats two and six of the eight beat count. This can be done in several ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several styles utilize On2 timing, including New York Style, Mambo On2, Eddie Torres Style, Mambo Palladium Style, Classic Mambo, and Son Cubano. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How the step is counted can vary within the On2 styles.  The Palladium style basic step counts its steps as "2-3-4, 6-7-8".  One can also count the steps by reciting "quick quick slow, quick quick slow", with the first &lt;code&gt;quick&lt;/code&gt; on beat two, and a &lt;code&gt;slow&lt;/code&gt; step on beats 4&amp;amp;5, and on beats 8&amp;amp;1. It is like On1, but delayed a beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though Eddie Torres style uses On2 timing, it counts its steps as "1-2-3, 5-6-7", just like the classic On1 style illustrated above. If counting the steps by reciting "quick quick slow, quick quick slow", then the first &lt;code&gt;quick&lt;/code&gt; occurs when the leader's right foot returns to center on beat one, with a &lt;code&gt;slow&lt;/code&gt; step on beats 3&amp;amp;4 and on beats 7&amp;amp;8. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another defining characteristic of a style of salsa dance is whether the dancers tend to travel along a line or circle around each other.  Traveling along a line is known as “in the slot”. LA Style and New York style are “in the slot”, and are also referred to as “crossbody” styles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;On1, In the Slot:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;iframe src='https://gfycat.com/ifr/GaseousLateIslandwhistler' frameborder='0' scrolling='no' allowfullscreen width='640' height='404'&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href="https://gfycat.com/gaseouslateislandwhistler"&gt;Salsa With Silvia via Gfycat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a circular style, the dancers revolve around each other. A workable analogy is to compare crossbody styles with West Coast Swing, whereas circular styles are akin to East Coast Swing. Cuban Style is a circular style, as is Casino Rueda Style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Circular:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;iframe src='https://makeagif.com/i/us3_hw' frameborder='0' scrolling='no' allowfullscreen width='400' height='300'&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ndN6srZ1XQs"&gt;Leo Martínez Salsa Cubana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Yet other styles!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though many of the core elements are common among styles of salsa dance, styles use their own terminology for many terms.  Know that &lt;a href="https://torontodancesalsa.ca/blog/the-different-styles-of-salsa/"&gt;salsa dance is regional&lt;/a&gt;. Having a vocabulary and an eye for the component building blocks will help understand other styles. That said, be forewarned that other styles and even regions that appear similar may use a different vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We covered just a few of the &lt;a href="https://www.danceus.org/salsa/different-salsa-styles-vocabulary"&gt;many styles&lt;/a&gt; of salsa dance.  There are &lt;a href="https://www.dancerhangout.com/articles/beginner-s-corner/4494-salsa-dance-styles?r=567-Salsa-Dance-Styles"&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; not mentioned above, including Puerto Rican Style, Colombian Style, Cali Style, Miami Style, Cuban Style, and Ballroom Style Salsa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about salsa dance check out these books:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-positions/id1513830159"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Dance-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B084FBB468"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=yBXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-patterns/id1513834201"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-1"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Patterns-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B093P9WS9H"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=1BXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Butterfly Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B094311BLN"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Handbook of Salsa Dance</title><link href="https://salsahandbook.github.io/output/salsa-handbooks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-16T11:37:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-16T12:57:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Marisol Enchufa</name></author><id>tag:salsahandbook.github.io,2020-05-16:/output/salsa-handbooks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This lists books in the Handbook of Salsa Series. It also provides where they are available for purchase and how to follow the author.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Introducing the &lt;em&gt;Handbook of Salsa Dance&lt;/em&gt; series. There are three books in this series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-positions/id1513830159"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Dance-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B084FBB468"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=yBXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-patterns/id1513834201"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-1"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Patterns-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B093P9WS9H"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=1BXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Butterfly Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B094311BLN"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Handbook of Salsa Dance Series&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This series covers beginner to intermediate level dance elements. This includes handholds, positions, patterns, and combinations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A salsa dance combination is comprised of two or more salsa dance patterns, each pattern covering two bars of music. Every salsa dance pattern begins and ends in a dance position. One can view the salsa dance pattern as the artful transition from a start position to an end position over eight beats of music. Because salsa dance is made up of combinations, and combinations are made up of patterns, one can view salsa dance as an aesthetically pleasing progression through a series of dance positions over the course of a song. Expert salsa dancers know how to get into and out of myriad salsa dance positions in interesting ways. Knowing how to do this can help increase your salsa dance repertoire.  This is facilitated by knowing your dance positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn how to break down elaborate salsa combinations into individual components by name. This allows you to pick up new patterns more quickly. It also makes it easier to remember a pattern or combination you learned previously. This will help you to learn from other dancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each handbook contains links to free online lessons that demonstrate the techniques. The author researched hundreds of websites and online video lessons and curated the best 148 of them for beginner and intermediate students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Positions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/positions-paperback.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To best understand combinations and patterns, know your positions. To truly know your positions, be able to identify them and call them by name. This handbook will show you how to do that. The key insight is that every pattern begins with a start position, and finishes with an end position. This handbook enumerates those positions and teaches the names. Once you learn the position names you will be able to write down a combination in terms of its patterns, by giving the start and end position of each pattern in the combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contents include a compendium of 68 salsa dance positions illustrated with 330 figures, an annotated curated list of 84 links to free online lessons from expert instructors, and a comprehensive dictionary of salsa dance terminology, packed into 387 pages. Each position is illustrated from multiple angles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/poses.v3/pairing3/p46-fl.png" width="200" height="350" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This handbook will help you identify common elements of salsa dance by name.  When you have the vocabulary to describe the building blocks, you can understand what you see on the dance floor. You’ll be able to break down a combination into component patterns. You’ll be able to identify the positions that make up a pattern. Then you will then be able to compose new patterns of your own. Expert salsa dancers know how to get into and out of myriad salsa dance positions in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salsa dance elements covered in this handbook include steps, handholds, turns, combs, arm and leg stylings, positions, patterns, and combinations. Handholds covered include left to right hold, right to left hold, parallel hold, handshake hold, reverse handshake hold, cross hold, and reverse cross hold. Turns covered include cross body lead, reverse cross body lead, single right turn, single left turn, inside turn, outside turn, and enchufa turn. Positions covered include apart positions, open position, closed position, half open position, handshake hold, hammerlock, half Hammerlock, cross hold, reverse cross hold, neck loop, arm hook, cuddle, butterfly, sombrero, and wraps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This handbook also comes in an ebook version.  The ebook version is ideally suited for referencing via smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where to find :&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-positions/id1513830159"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Dance-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B084FBB468"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=yBXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/patterns-paperback.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second book in this series shows how to break down patterns into constituent dance elements.  It also shows how to create combinations from patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Handbook provides a breakdown of common positions, holds, turns, and patterns. It contains 36 dance positions, 51 dance patterns, and 184 illustrations, all packed into 293 pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A salsa dance combination is comprised of two or more dance patterns, each pattern covering two bars of music. Every salsa dance pattern begins and ends in a dance position. One can view the salsa dance pattern as the artful transition from a start position to an end position over eight beats of music. Because salsa dance is made up of combinations, and combinations are made up of patterns, one can view salsa dance as an aesthetically pleasing progression through a series of dance patterns over the course of a song. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/poses.v3/pairing2/p50-fr.png" width="150" height="262" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those amazing dancers that you see on the dance floor seem to have an endless knowledge base of elaborate combinations. How can they memorize so many different combinations? The secret is that many of them tend to use a small collection of patterns. They know how to get into and out of a position. If they have a combination that begins with some particular start position, they also know an interesting way to get into that position. Each pattern they perform takes them from the start position to an end position. They know how to take that end position and turn it into a start position for the next pattern. They know how to mix and match patterns to create combinations that seem to be infinitely varied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This handbook will help you get there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This handbook is structured for quick reference. This handbook contains a compendium of basic positions and turns, a catalog of common salsa dance patterns, a collection of salsa pattern combinations composed of patterns defined here, and a guide to creating new pattern combinations of your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patterns in this handbook can be used to create thousands of combinations. It is possible to combine these patterns into 227 combinations of length three without repeating a pattern within any of those 227 combinations. The number of combinations that can be created without repeating a pattern is even greater for longer combinations: 471 combinations of length 4, 952 combinations of length 5, and 1,820 combinations of length 6. Twelve combinations are provided to show how to create combinations using the patterns in the handbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where to find :&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-patterns/id1513834201"&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/illustrated-handbook-of-salsa-dance-1"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Handbook-Salsa-Patterns-Marisol-Enchufa-ebook/dp/B093P9WS9H"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books/about?id=1BXmDwAAQBAJ"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Illustrated Handbook of Salsa Dance: &lt;strong&gt;Butterfly Patterns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/butterfly-patterns.png" width="333" height="500" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newest handbook in this series focuses on one type of salsa dance element: the butterfly position. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a comprehensive exploration of myriad butterfly positions. Whether you learn best from illustrations, diagrams, descriptions, or video, this handbook has you covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/poses.v3/pairing6/p40b-fl.png" width="225" height="400" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This handbook breaks down 5 categories of variations on butterfly patterns. Each set of variations combines common butterfly positions, holds, turns into patterns. Each focuses on a single objective, such as entering a butterfly position, exiting a butterfly position, and using a butterfly position in the middle part of a pattern. These variations comprise 20 dance positions, 40 dance patterns, 131 illustrations. This handbook shows how to combine these patterns into enough combinations to fill an entire night of dancing without once repeating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas the first two handbooks in this series take a breadth approach to learning, this handbook takes a depth approach. By mastering a single category of patterns you can accelerate your learning in areas. Instead of slowly learning everything across the board, diving deep into a single type of position and pattern takes your dancing to a new level. This handbook focuses on the Butterfly positions and their related patterns. It looks at what can be done using 9 butterfly positions. From these 9 positions it presents 20 patterns that use a butterfly position. It provides another 20 patterns that complement the butterfly combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;img src="images/Positions/poses.v3/pairing6/p40a-l.png" width="225" height="400" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 40 patterns can be combined to create hundreds of short combinations and thousands of longer combinations. These patterns can create 620 combinations of length three, and 2,349 combinations of length four, where each combination never uses any single pattern more than once. Based just on the patterns in this handbook, you could literally dance all night without repeating yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This handbook provides 5 sets of variations that show how to get into and out of butterfly positions. You can devise many combinations of your own creation. This handbook shows how. To show how to combine patterns into combinations, 11 combinations are provided, of which 9 are linked to a video lesson. Each combination demonstrates how to combine the patterns presented into a pleasing sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Where to find :&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B094311BLN"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>